Clearinghouse Resources for Educators of Adults (CREA) Records
Clearinghouse Resources for Educators of Adults (CREA) Records
1975-1981
Syracuse University, Clearinghouse of Resources for Educators of Adults
3.5 linear ft.
Administrative files, correspondence, proposals, and publications of the Clearinghouse Resources for Educators of Adults at Syracuse University. Correspondence of significant duration or amount includes Charters, Alexander N.; Rivera, William; Holmwood, Donald; and the State Education Department.
2458678
Biographical History
The Clearinghouse Resources for Educators of Adults (CREA) began operation as a state-wide grant-funded program at Syracuse University (Syracuse, NY) in November 1975. Its stated purpose was to provide access to and information on professional development material aimed at administrators, teachers, counselors, and others working in adult and continuing education. CREA identified, acquired, cataloged and housed some 1800 relevant print and non-print items which it then made available for loan to New York State educators. CREA also developed and published a number of subject-matter bibliographies on topics such as English as a Second Language (ESL), administration and management, teacher education, and program development and instructional techniques. Eventually its mission expanded to include organizing or offering regional workshops and colloquia on topics related to adult and continuing education. CREA operated until 1981, when the State Education Department (Albany, NY) declined to renew its funding.
Donald P. Holmwood served as director of CREA from 1975 to 1978, after which William Rivera assumed leadership.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Clearinghouse Resources for Educators of Adults (CREA) Records comprise the files of the organization over its six-year lifespan. The collection consists of administrative files, correspondence, financial information, printed material, promotional material, proposal forms and instructions, proposals themselves, publications and reports.
Administrative files contains collection information, order forms and mailing lists, policies and procedures, etc. Correspondence holds business correspondence and includes directors, graduate assistants and others who worked with or for CREA at Syracuse University as well as correspondence with external organizations such as the State Education Department (SED) and ERIC. Of particular interest is the material on CREA refunding, as it demonstrated the support for and usefulness of CREA. Financial information includes budget amendments (because CREA was grant-funded, budget amendments exceeding $500 or 10% required approval from SED) as well as internal ledgers and account printouts. Printed material and Promotional material offer clippings, press releases and other instances of CREA in the news.
As a grant-funded program which operated on a year-to-year basis, CREA had to reapply each year for renewal of its funding from SED. Proposal forms and instructions contains the requirements for these applications, while Proposals contains drafts, revisions and final versions of all six proposals submitted by CREA to SED. (This material has been organized as well as possible, given that xerox copies of previous budgets and proposals were often marked up as drafts for later versions, so that dates are not always definitive.)
CREA was an active disseminator of information, and Publications includes articles and papers by CREA staff members, subject matter bibliographies, and complete or nearly-complete runs of the CREA newsletter, CREA-tivity in New York, and the Federal Register Review. Reports is divided into reports about CREA (e.g. quarterly and annual progress reports, expense reports, and final evaluations) which were required by the SED, and reports by CREA, whch include a variety of internal evaluations, surveys, assessments, white papers, and project evaluations.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, see also the papers of Dr. Alexander Charters, who was directly connected with CREA.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Charters, Alexander N.; Hiemstra, Roger.; Rivera, William McLeod, 1934-; Syracuse University. -- Clearinghouse of Resources for Educators of Adults.; CREA-tivity in New York.; Federal Register Review.; Adult education -- New York (State); Adult education teachers -- Training of.; Articles.; Brochures.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Manuscripts (document genre); Proposals.; Reports.; Adult education teachers.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Clearinghouse Resources for Educators of Adults (CREA), 1982.
Inventory
- Administrative files
  - Collection information, undated
  - Director search, 1979
  - Dissemination plan, undated
  - Information file (Holmwood), 1976
  - Needs assessment
    See also Reports: By CREA: "CREA Needs Assessment: A Report on User Needs in New York State"
    - "Central New York Needs Assessment Project in Continuing Ed", 1977
    - "Michigan Adult Basic Education Needs Assessment", 1978
  - Orders
    - Forms
    - List of publishers, undated
    - Mailing list, 1975-1979
    - Requests for CREA material, 1980-1981
  - Policies and procedures, 1976-1978
  - Position descriptions
  - Proposals
    - ADELL proposal, 1977
      See also Correspondence: ADELL
    - Special education proposal, 1980
  - Pyrex
  - Resource units, 1979; undated
  - Section 309 programs
    - New York, 1975-1976
    - Other states (alpha by state)
  - Solicitation letters, 1980-1981
  - Summary of activities, 1976-1978
  - Miscellaneous
- Correspondence
  Letters are generally filed under their originator in chronological order. If multiple copies existed in the files, copies may also be filed under recipient, if appropriate. All communication from the State Education Department (Albany, NY) is filed together under that name, regardless of the individual sender.
  - ADELL, 1977-1978
    See also Administrative files: Proposals: ADELL
  - Adelphi University, 1977
  - Carr, Neil W., See State Education Department (Albany, New York)
  - Charters, Alexander N., 1975-1980; undated
  - CREA refunding, 1981
  - ERIC/EPSIS, 1978-1979; undated
  - Gooler, Dennis, 1979-1981
  - Greenfest, Michael, See Rivera, William M.
  - Gschwender, Ed, 1978-1980
  - Hatfield, John N., See State Education Department (Albany, New York)
  - Hiemstra, Roger, 1980
  - Holmwood, Donald P.
    - General correspondence, 1975-1978
    - Notes, 1975-1978
  - Johnson, Harvey J., See State Education Department (Albany, New York)
  - Matheson, Lois A., See State Education Department (Albany, New York)
  - Murphy, Garrett, See State Education Department (Albany, New York)
  - New York Association for Continuing Education (NYACE)/New York Association for Continuing and Community Education (NYACCE), 1975-1980
  - Office of Sponsored Programs (Syracuse University), 1976-1980
  - Patchen, William L., See Office of Sponsored Programs (Syracuse University)
  - Poczik, Robert, See State Education Department (Albany, New York)
  - Purga, Robert, See State Education Department (Albany, New York)
  - Regional Learning Service of Central New York, 1980
  - Reiss, Mary, See State Education Department (Albany, New York)
  - Rivera, William M., 1979-1981; also includes correspondence of Michael Greenfest, assistant to director
    See also Publications: CREA: Articles and papers by CREA staff
  - State Education Department (Albany, New York), 1975-1981; 2 folders
  - Miscellaneous
    - Internal (within CREA and/or Syracuse University), 1976-1981
    - External, 1977-1980
- Financial
  - Budget amendments (Forms FA-10A), 1977-1981
  - Ledgers and account printouts, 1978-1981
  - Travel expenses (Forms FA-60), 1978-1980
  - Miscellaneous (by date), 1976-1981
- Printed material
  - Clippings, 1977-1981
- Publicity
  - Press releases, 1975-1976; undated
  - Miscellaneous, 1976; 1979-1980
- Proposal forms and instructions
  - State Education Department [SED]
    See also Correspondence: State Education Department (Albany, NY)
    - 1975
    - 1976
    - 1977
    - 1981
  - Syracuse University Proposal Information Checklists, undated
- Proposals
  - Conditions of approval, undated
  - Excerpts, 1975-1978
  - Excerpts, 1978-1980
  - 1975-1976, drafts, budget
  - 1976-1977, draft, proposal and budget, proposal and budget with revisions, budget with revisions, budget with revisions, amendments
  - 1977-1978, drafts, proposal with budget, budget only
  - 1978-1979, drafts, proposal and budget with revisions, drafts incorporating revisions, budget (partial)
  - Supplementary proposal, 1979
  - 1979-1980, drafts, budget
  - 1980-1981, proposal w/o budget, several versions of budget with revisions
- Publications
  - CREA
    - Articles and papers by CREA staff
    - Bibliographies
    - CREA newsletter (continued as CREA-tivity in New York), 1976-1981
    - CREA-tivity in New York, 1981
    - Federal Register Review, 1977-1981
      See also Reports: By CREA: Federal Register Review evaluation
    - "Learning to Read Should Make Sense", undated
    - Professional Development series, 1978
    - "A Research Study Aimed at the Adaptation of Tasks for the Measurement of Logical Judgment in Adults", undated
    - Miscellaneous, brochures etc
  - Non-CREA
    - Articles and papers
    - Miscellaneous
- Reports
  - About CREA
    - Internal reports, 1978-1980
    - Progress reports
      - Quarterly, 1976-1981; 2 folders
      - Annual, 1979; 1980
    - Final Evaluations
      - Excerpts, 1975-1977
      - 1975-1976
      - 1976-1977
      - 1978-1979
      - 1979-1980, draft appendices; 2 folders
      - 1979-1980, 2 folders
    - Final Expenditure Report (Form FA-10-F), 1975-1976
    - Final reports
      - 1977-1978
      - 1978-1979
  - By CREA
    - "Clearinghouse Resources for Educators of Adults 1975-1979", report with drafts; 2 folders
    - "Comparative Study of the CREA: Two-Year Existence", 1978
    - "CREA Needs Assessment: A Report on User Needs in New York State", 1980
      See also Administrative files: Needs assessment
    - "CREA Through 1983: A Middle-Range Plan", 1980
    - "Designing a Comprehensive Professional Development Program for Educators of Adults: The CREA Experience", [1978?]
    - "Evaluation Report on the Inventory Conducted by the Clearinghouse of Resources for Educators of Adults Collection", undated
    - Federal Register Review evaluation, 1979
      See also Publications: CREA: Federal Register Review
    - "Formative Evaluation of CREA", undated
    - "Older Adults Educational Interest Survey", 1979
    - "Project Evaluation FY 80/81", 1981
    - "Proposed CREA Participation in New York State 310 Project Dissemination", 1979
    - "Third Quarter Program Review FY 81/82”, 1981
    - Unidentified report (draft), 1976
  - Unidentified draft/notes, 1978